<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Files on Alexander Pino</title>
    <link>https://a-pino.github.io/files/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Files on Alexander Pino</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>alex.pino.salig@gmail.com (Alexander Pino)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>alex.pino.salig@gmail.com (Alexander Pino)</webMaster>
      <atom:link href="https://a-pino.github.io/files/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Research Internship Poster - Computer Vision</title>
      <link>https://a-pino.github.io/files/matsuda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>alex.pino.salig@gmail.com (Alexander Pino)</author>
      <guid>https://a-pino.github.io/files/matsuda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;instance-segmentation-and-classification-of-bacterial-micrographs&#34;&gt;Instance Segmentation and Classification of Bacterial Micrographs&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Alexander Pino, supervised by Hideo Matsuda, PhD and Shigeto Seno, PhD&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Presented at &lt;em&gt;FrontierLab@OsakaU&lt;/em&gt;, July 31, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://a-pino.github.io/files/matsuda.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Instance S&amp;hellip; poster&#34; title=&#34;Instance S... poster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undergraduate Thesis - Topological Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://a-pino.github.io/files/thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>alex.pino.salig@gmail.com (Alexander Pino)</author>
      <guid>https://a-pino.github.io/files/thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;using-topology-to-extract-insights-from-uaap-basketball-data&#34;&gt;Using Topology to Extract Insights from UAAP Basketball Data&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Authors: Benjamin Louis Ang, Alexander Pino Jr., Dane Lauren Rosario&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-manuscript&#34;&gt;Full manuscript&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;https://a-pino.github.io/files/Ang_Pino_Rosario_Manuscript_430.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to read the paper in full.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Basketball is one of the most popular team sports, whose many compet-&#xA;itive, well-organized and well-recorded leagues provide rich sources of data&#xA;frequently used to analyze tactics, strategy, player performance and team&#xA;composition. A consequence of basketball’s team dynamics, comprising five&#xA;active players per team on the court who may be replaced by substitute&#xA;players on many occasions per game, is the formation of archetypes; players&#xA;are categorized into positions based on roles they play, such as point-scoring,&#xA;rebounding or defense. However, the evolution of game strategy has meant&#xA;that the three traditional positions, namely—guard, forward, and center, are&#xA;no longer sufficient to completely describe roles of players within the team.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Understanding the archetypes of basketball players offers an advantage to&#xA;teams in strategizing against their opponents, and finding and fixing weak-&#xA;nesses in their team composition, whether by adding skills to current players&#xA;or recruiting new talent. Usually a matter of subjective observation, espe-&#xA;cially in non-professional leagues such as the collegiate University Athletics&#xA;Association of the Philippines (UAAP), we undertake the task of finding&#xA;groups of players who fit in certain positions or archetypes more objectively&#xA;with mathematical techniques from topological data analysis (TDA).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We use numerical data measuring player performance during the 84th&#xA;season of the UAAP basketball tournament, with a high number of fea-&#xA;tures per player corresponding to different player actions such as points, re-&#xA;bounds, assists, steals, blocks, turnovers, fouls and shot attempts. Using this&#xA;high-dimensional dataset as a point cloud, we use Vietoris-Rips filtration to&#xA;connect nodes representing players from progressively longer distances, dis-&#xA;covering the presence of hole complexes that imply groupings or clusters of&#xA;players. We study our dataset further using the Mapper algorithm which&#xA;applies dimensionality reduction and clustering to more prominently display&#xA;topological features as connections between nodes representing multiple play-&#xA;ers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are able to identify four subgroups of players not previously indi-&#xA;cated in the five traditional basketball positions; paint dominators, stretch&#xA;forwards, defensive rebounders, and scrappers. Furthermore, we discover two&#xA;hole structures of a much larger prominence than others in the mapper plot,&#xA;associating them with missing archetypes of players. These are three-point&#xA;plus defensive specialists, and aggressive foul-drawers, whose attributes are&#xA;currently underrepresented within the league, and thus could make a team to&#xA;strategize against. We conclude that TDA techniques can identify archetypes&#xA;of players beyond the traditional classifications and can provide advantageous&#xA;insights for basketball teams.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
